Guide to the Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning records,1832-1897.
Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning records,1832-1897
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning records, 1832-1897.
6079
Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning (Corning, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records of the Painted Post Circuit quarterly conference meeting (1832-1839) and the Painted Post Church (1832-1833); records of the leader's minutes for the Corning circuit, and quarterly conference meeting minutes for the Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning. Also Class Number One's class leader's records (1839-1844), Trustee's annual meeting minutes (1857-1897) and a register listing the history of, statistics about and a subscription list for the church built in 1861; marriage, probationer's, membership and class lists. Subjects discussed include slavery, temperance, a missionary society, revivals and church discipline.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
In 1832 Painted Post was set off as a separate circuit containing (as of 1837) Little Flatts, Painted Post, "Addison Village", West Addison, Erwin Centre, Campbell and Tioga. In 1833 a class formed at Caton, which was set off with Corning in November 1839. Another division occurred in 1843 when Erwin, Painted Post and Campbell formed a circuit named after the latter two towns. In 1861-62, the Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning built a church which seated 700.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Item 1 contains records of the Painted Post Circuit Quarterly Conference Meeting (1832-1839, Parts A,D) and the Painted Post Church (Part C, 1832-33); records of the leader's minutes for the Coming Circuit (Part B, 1841-44); Quarterly Conference minutes for the Corning Circuit (Part E, 1839-1846) and Quarterly Conference meeting minutes for the Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning (Part F, December 1847-1867). The collection also includes Class No. 1's class leader's records (1839-1844); Trustee's annual meeting minutes (1857-1897); and a register listing the history of, statistics about and a subscription list for the church built in 1861; marriage, probationer's records, and class and membership lists. Subjects discussed include slavery, temperance, a missionary society, revivals and church discipline.
(Note: Sections of this book were in different parts of the volume -right-side up, upside-down, back to front and vice versa.)
SUBJECTS
Names:
Methodist Episcopal Church of Corning (Corning, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Methodist Episcopal Church--New York (State)--Painted Post.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Painted Post.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Corning.; Methodist Episcopal Church--New York (State)--Corning.; Antislavery movements.; Church discipline.; Temperance and religion--New York (State)--Corning.
Places:
Steuben County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Painted Post (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Corning (N.Y.--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Records of the Painted Post Circuit, Item 1
  (Note: See the Collection Description for a breakdown of contents.) Items of note are as follows:
  - Section A
    Inside cover contains a steward's record listing the number of adults and children and the budget for 1835. Contains meeting minutes for October 9, 1842.
  - Section B: Coming Circuit Leader's Meetings.
    - September 29, 1841
      A committee is appointed to build a parsonage.
    - July 21, 1844
      Reports of a Sunday School.
  - Section D
    - p. 2, December 22, 1822
      Resolved to form a tract society and to promote the cause of temperance.
    - p. 3, June 15, 1833
      Resolved to form a Benevolent Society to include sabbath schools, tract and missionary work and other purposes.
    - p. 8, August 2, 1834
      Resolved to form a missionary society.
    - p. 9, n.d. 1835
      Resolution on supporting temperance societies.
    - p. 13, February 20, 1836
      Resolution concerning "Wesley's Rule of Discipline" on the use of ardent spirits.
    - p. 31, July 27, 1839
      Last Meeting
  - Section E: Quarterly Conference Minutes for the Corning Circuit
    - p. 33, November 1839
      Discussion of recent division of the circuit.
    - p. 37
      Curriculum for prospective elders and deacons includes English grammar.
    - p. 42, July 24, 1841
      License denied to a man charged with trifling with the affections of a female.
    - p. 48-49, January 29, 1842
      Resolution on slavery.
    - p. 58, November 12, 1842
      Collection taken for the Wesleyan Genesee Seminary.
    - p. 61, February 4, 1843
      Member required to give a statement "in love feast".
    - p. 69, July 15, 1843
      The church requests a conference to divide the circuit and to make a station of Corning with Caton as an appointment. Painted Post and Campbell Circuit would have Erwin appointed with it.
    - p. 71, July 15, 1843
      The first of a series of yearly reports on Sunday schools.
    - p. 90-91, August 22, 1846
      Reports on a dispute over the pastor which has been disrupting the church.
    - p. 93, August 17, 1843
      Last entry.
  - Section F: Quarterly Meeting Minutes for the M.E. Church of Corning
    - p. 96
      First meeting.
    - p. 111, March 14, 1850
      Resolved to join with Lawrenceville to hold a camp meeting.
    - n.p., February 1, 1863
      Reports of an improvement in spirituality and new converts.
    - 1861-62 meeting to 1867-68 meeting - gap.
- Class No. 1 Leader's Book (September 1839-1844), Item 2
  After four pages of printed "General Rules of the United Methodist Societies" are lists of members and their attendance at class meetings (1839-1844). The front and back inside covers contain exhortations.
- Trustee's Record Book, 1850, Item 3
  - Part A: Trustee's Annual Meeting Minutes, 1850-1897
    Records the annual election of trustees and matters pertaining to the temporal life of the church. Items of note include:
    - July 9, 1850: Meeting to incorporate.
    - September-October 1860: Plans to build a new church.
    - May 8, 1861-December 1861: Discussion of pew rent.
    - After June 21, 1864 is inserted the "Berea lesson for 1874"
    - Quarterly conference minutes for August 5, 1876.
  - Part B: Quarterly Conference Meeting Minutes ( 1862-? )
- Register, 1853-1869., Item 4
  - Section I.
    Record of baptisms includes date, name, residence, officiating minister and witnesses.
  - Section II.
    Record of marriages includes date, names of parties and their place of residence, officiating minister and witnesses. [note: after section II there is a history of the construction of the church with statistics and a list of "Receipts for the church," September 1862.]
  - Section III.
    Record for probationers (1856-1862) includes date, name, condition, residence, church relationship and remarks.
  - Section IV.
    Membership lists (alphabetical) includes name, residence, time and mode of joining, class leader and remarks. Continued after section V.
  - Section V.
    Record of the classes lists class members and remarks under the leader's name.